William Mukere

(254) 700548272

william.mukere@gmail.com

Nairobi, Kenya

https://www.linkedin.com/in/willliammukere/

SUMMARY/OBJECTIVE



Data-driven expert with 5 years' experience in Insurance industry majorly in claims analysis and mitigation of cost, underwriting of risks for individual clients and scheme management. Led successful implementation of several health insurance products and products revamped. I have won three awards in innovation of various insurance products, robotic process automation for internal systems and members management. Looking for an opportunity in a data driven company where creativity is encouraged and where I can combine my skills in research together with knowledge and experience in various Data Analytics and technological tools to achieve company's success.

WORK EXPERIENCE



UNDERWRITING ANALYST

Jubilee Health Insurance | Nairobi | April 2019 - Present

- Created Dashboard using Excel and Power Bi to evaluate retail business daily performance. This led to well representation of business booked on daily basis.
- Led the successful implementation of e-cards project. Thus, reducing the cost of card issuance from KES 250 to KES 5.
- Automated reports using Power Query and Power pivot.
- Planned and executed a distribution channel of reports using Power Query, one drive and SharePoint.
- Created a tracking report using excel for e-policy documents. Leading to a reduction in TAT of sending policy documents from 7 days to 2 days.
- Created a tracking report to measure TATs for business processing unit team and call Centre actioned task.
- Implemented shift from issuance of hardcopy policy documents to e-policy documents. Thus, leading to reduction in TAT of policy document issuance from 7 days to 2 days from day of policy activation.
- Created a database for analysis and management of acknowledgement and comments from clients. This led to an increase in acknowledgement emails from 20% to 45%.
- Automated e-policy documents dispatch using VBA code. Thus, leading to reduction in TAT from 7 days to 2 days.
- Automated edit of receipt reports using Macro and Excel VBA.

CLAIMS ANALYST

Jubilee Health Insurance | Nairobi | February 2018 - April 2019

- Proposed claims cost management strategy that led to a reduction of claim ratio from 75% to 69%.
- Supported the growth of e-claims providers from 6 hospitals to 100 hospitals. Leading to timely receipts of claims and payment of the same.
- Managed implementation of Claims custom rule extensions and several other medical projects under digital and innovation.
- Conducted trainings on use of internal systems and applications.
- Carried analysis of claims with errors and recommended ways of solving duplicate claims errors and zero amount invoice errors. Thus, led to less than 1% error rate.
- Managed a team of 5 e-claims registrars and acted as a team leader to ensure task were done on time.
- Analyzed claims on document management extension database and shared daily report on the same.

ASSISTANT CLAIMS ANALYST

UAP Old Mutual Insurance | Nairobi | November 2017 - February 2018

- Carried excise of retrieving old claims data from paper archives and successful uploading them to data warehouse for ease of access.
- Conducted a mapping excise to map hospitals under UAP providers' panel.
- Analyzed claims data to pick patterns and trends for purpose of recommendations of fraud mitigation strategy to the management.
- Performed data entry of invoices of hospitals claims.

SKILLS

- Innovation
- Detail-oriented
- Resourcefulness
- Analytical

- Power Bi
- Excel
- Python for Data Analysis (Pandas, Matplotlib, seaborn and NumPy)
- R

EDUCATION

Name of School: University of Nairobi

Degree: MSc Social Statistics

Years: 2020 - Present

City, Country: Nairobi, Kenya

Name of School: University of Nairobi

Degree: Bachelor of Economics and Statistics

Years: 2013 - 2016

City, Country: Nairobi, Kenya

CERTIFICATIONS/LICENSES

- Data Analysis in R DataQuest.io
- Introduction to Data Science in Python DataCamp
- Statistical Packages (R, Stata and SPSS) University of Nairobi
- Customer Services Alison





